<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-01-03T14:17:34-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">constrained creativity</title><subtitle>writing every day. minimal editing. done better than perfect.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">seneca and alan watts on dying and living</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/seneca-and-alan-on-dying-and-living/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="seneca and alan watts on dying and living" /><published>2016-12-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/seneca-and-alan-on-dying-and-living</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/seneca-and-alan-on-dying-and-living/">&lt;p&gt;there is some tension between these three quotes below, but they’re related for me. the first two are from seneca’s letter to lucilius titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Moral_letters_to_Lucilius/Letter_77&quot;&gt;‘on taking one’s own life.’&lt;/a&gt;. the last is a quote from a popular talk by alan watts on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M7KRgluYeps&quot;&gt;the acceptance of death and the meaning of life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“An ordinary journey will be incomplete if you come to a stop in the middle of it, but life is never incomplete if it is an honourable one. At whatever point you leave life, if you leave it in the right way, it is a whole.” –– &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Moral_letters_to_Lucilius/Letter_77&quot;&gt;seneca, letter LXXVII&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Every life without exception is a short one… As it is with a play, so it is with life – what matters is not how long the acting lasts, but how good it is. It is not important at what point you stop. Stop wherever you will – only make sure that you round it off with a good ending.” –– &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Moral_letters_to_Lucilius/Letter_77&quot;&gt;seneca, letter LXXVII&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“No one imagines that a symphony is supposed to improve as it goes along, or that the whole object of playing is to reach the finale. The point of music is discovered in every moment of playing and listening to it. It is the same, I feel, with the greater part of our lives, and if we are unduly absorbed in improving them we may forget altogether to live them.” –– &lt;a href=&quot;www.goodreads.com/author/show/1501668.Alan_W_Watts&quot;&gt;alan w. watts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;as i sort of stew (in the best way) in my thinking about death this week, i keep coming back to an idea about living and dying. what keeps sticking is that we must be (culturally) afraid of dying because we haven’t figured out how to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;seneca’s line about life being complete as long as it’s honorable definitely reminds me of how i think about &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/141849731677/timelines-of-change-living-everyday-like-its-the&quot;&gt;living each day&lt;/a&gt;. the 2nd and 3rd quotes are, to me, similarly about the important of knowing how to live well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;there is a strange, but coherent irony in our fear of death as it manifests in our continued avoidance of the one question that would end that fear. how should one live?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;writing data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;mbtablestyle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;writing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9:22&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;spell-check, link-finding, &amp;amp; formatting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14:30&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">there is some tension between these three quotes below, but they’re related for me. the first two are from seneca’s letter to lucilius titled ‘on taking one’s own life.’. the last is a quote from a popular talk by alan watts on the acceptance of death and the meaning of life.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what ruins our characters…</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/what-ruins-our-characters/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what ruins our characters..." /><published>2016-12-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/what-ruins-our-characters</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/what-ruins-our-characters/">&lt;p&gt;another piece of this death thought bubble is another thing seneca said in one of his letters to lucilius. in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Moral_letters_to_Lucilius/Letter_83&quot;&gt;letter LXXXIII (83)&lt;/a&gt; he says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“For this is what makes us wicked: that no one of us looks back over his own life. Our thoughts are devoted only to what we are about to do. And yet our plans for the future always depend on the past.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i think this is true from the individual life up to the scale of geology. when we try to understand what’s possible moving forward without understanding what has happened in the past, we really just fuck it up. it might be not understanding where we come (family &amp;amp; place) from as individuals or where not seeing where the roots of our society and culture are. either way, when things go wrong, many times there are historical forces at play as well as present realities. sure, you may want to be an all-star athlete but if your parents didn’t teach you to be active when you were growing up, that’s a much bigger hindrance to your path than your occasional lack of motivation. that just puts you behind the ball of the person who’s parents are both college athletics coaches. it doesn’t make it impossible, but we should all at least be honest with the cards we’ve been dealt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i think a big flaw in our western, individualistic society is that we’re culturally trained to see ourselves as individuals. this shortsightedness really just obscures huge parts of our realities. if we could, individually and societally, take the time to look back at our lives and just reflect, i think we’d all be in better places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;as my buddy &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2quotes.tumblr.com/post/145586733722/life-is-really-just-about-shitty-models-and-their&quot;&gt;spencer once said&lt;/a&gt;, “life is really just about making shitty models and error correction.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i’m not totally sure how to handle moving america towards that as a country, but i can certainly start with myself. hence, my personal retreat…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;mbtablestyle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;writing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16:56&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;spell-check, link-finding, &amp;amp; formatting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;24:36&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">another piece of this death thought bubble is another thing seneca said in one of his letters to lucilius. in letter LXXXIII (83) he says:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">my personal retreat</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/my-personal-retreat/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="my personal retreat" /><published>2016-12-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/my-personal-retreat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/my-personal-retreat/">&lt;p&gt;a few people have asked what this is so i figured it was time to write it out. i’ve found that one of the highest values of writing out my thoughts is being able to direct people to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so. my personal retreat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-it&quot;&gt;what is it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it’s where i take some time at the beginning of the (gregorian) calendar year to focus on me.*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wherewhen-did-it-start&quot;&gt;where/when did it start?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in january 2015, my roommate, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.annemariegray.com/&quot;&gt;annemarie&lt;/a&gt; and i just went to a coffeeshop (RIP darwin’s ltd on mass ave. in cambridge, ma). i don’t totally remember why we did it, but it seemed like a good idea at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-you-do&quot;&gt;what do you do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if you want to see the long, detailed explanation of what i do, &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/154856740232/my-personal-retreat-long-version&quot;&gt;it’s over here&lt;/a&gt;. below is the agenda/checklist version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-1-1-jan-2017-review-2016&quot;&gt;day 1 (1 jan 2017): review 2016&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;review and finalize my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infinitegrowth.rocks&quot;&gt;infinite growth&lt;/a&gt; vision statement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;review and reflect on how i spent time in 2016 (details on this in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/154856740232/my-personal-retreat-long-version&quot;&gt;long version&lt;/a&gt;)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;guiding question: did my time spent align w/ my values?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;review annual budget&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-2-2-jan-2017-plan-for-2017&quot;&gt;day 2 (2 jan 2017): plan for 2017&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reconfigure calendar and time protocols
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;do monthly simple transaction edits&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plan budget&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;organize files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-3-3-jan-2017-project-launches&quot;&gt;day 3 (3 jan 2017): project launches&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;review &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/archive&quot;&gt;2016 writing&lt;/a&gt; for book theme(s)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;figure out tech infrastructure for &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/154072823022/why-ill-start-a-personal-email-newsletter&quot;&gt;my weekly email newsletter&lt;/a&gt; (probably &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyletter.com&quot;&gt;http://tinyletter.com&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;start running list of book reviews (&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/personal-growth/every-book-ive-read-in-2016-afedade17695#.v31iuuoeh&quot;&gt;inspiration&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;figure out infrastructure for writing group (probably &lt;a href=&quot;http://groups.io&quot;&gt;http://groups.io&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;start &lt;a href=&quot;lqb2reads.tumblr.com/archive&quot;&gt;things i read&lt;/a&gt; timelines on github (hopefully based on willob’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.will-ob.com/dvorak/&quot;&gt;custom timeline tool&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;figure out infrastructure for emoji faces book project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;write out vision and initial framework for secret project with annemarie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;writing data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;mbtablestyle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;writing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15:34&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;spell-check, link-finding, &amp;amp; formatting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;??:??&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">a few people have asked what this is so i figured it was time to write it out. i’ve found that one of the highest values of writing out my thoughts is being able to direct people to them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">my personal retreat (long version)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/my-personal-retreat-long-version/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="my personal retreat (long version)" /><published>2016-12-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/my-personal-retreat-long-version</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/my-personal-retreat-long-version/">&lt;p&gt;a few people have asked what this is so i figured it was time to write it out. i’ve found that one of the highest values of writing out my thoughts is being able to direct people to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so. my personal retreat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-it&quot;&gt;what is it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it’s where i take some time at the beginning of the (gregorian) calendar year to focus on me.*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wherewhen-did-it-start&quot;&gt;where/when did it start?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in january 2015, my roommate, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.annemariegray.com/&quot;&gt;annemarie&lt;/a&gt; and i just went to a coffeeshop (RIP darwin’s ltd on mass ave. in cambridge, ma). i don’t totally remember why we did it, but it seemed like a good idea at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-you-do&quot;&gt;what do you do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if you want to see the short version, &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/154856829847/my-personal-retreat&quot;&gt;it’s over here&lt;/a&gt;. below is the long, detailed version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;generally, what i do is spend some time reflecting on the past year and then making some plans for the next year. it’s gotten more detailed each year, but the point is to look back and then look forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;that first year i was using a tool that &lt;a href=&quot;http://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0031/5352/files/ReflectionWorkshopPromptsForNewsletter.pdf?utm_campaign=Reflecting+on+2014+%28Master%29+%28dkAA3z%29&amp;amp;36663=&amp;amp;_ke=bHFiQG1pdC5lZHU%3D&amp;amp;utm_source=Master+Holstee+Newsletter+List+-+Weekly&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&quot;&gt;holstee&lt;/a&gt; had sent out via email. i think i ignored the first page but pages two and three really made me think differently about my time and life. i can still trace elements from that exercise to how i think about these things now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;make a list of your guiding values&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;look back at your previous year and see how your spent your time&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;compare how you spent your time with your values&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;if they match up, make no changes. if they don’t, adjust your personal system (in the form of what an ideal week looks like) as necessary&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;that might be a little vague so here’s what i do specifically:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-1-review-and-reflect&quot;&gt;part 1: review and reflect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;review-my-calendar&quot;&gt;1. review my calendar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i use my calendar rigorously. i even go back and make sure that i delete things that didn’t happen. this type of usage makes it a very helpful tool for reviewing how i spend my time. and, of course, how we spend our days is how we spend our lives. [quote?] so i go through and write down the highlights of how i spent my time, week-by-week. it looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;## week 7 (feb 9-15)

- dinner with clara and caroline howe
- attend presencing forum with otto scharmer, dayna cunningham, phil thompson, etc.
- chatted with robert hacker about 100k business plan pitch
- had interview with the food project about crew leader position over summer
- filed 2013 taxes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;think-through-my-values&quot;&gt;2. think through my values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i don’t really have a structure for this but it mostly is just a list of things that are important to me. justice, love, rest, friendships, travel, whatever. it has actually been more important than i thought it would be to revisit these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;review-my-time-spent-through-the-lens-of-my-values&quot;&gt;3. review my time spent through the lens of my values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;look back at the week summaries and see how spending my time did or didn’t align with my values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;review-my-budget&quot;&gt;4. review my budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;look back at my previous year’s budget plan (that first year i didn’t have one so i just made one up by looking at my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mint.com&quot;&gt;http://www.mint.com&lt;/a&gt; data).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;then, because i use simple, i can get a pretty quick high-level view of where i actually spent my money. i usually take about an hour to go through and clean things up: making sure things are in the right categories, adding detail where needed (mostly remembering why i took out cash), etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;then i compare my projected budget to my actual budget. i’m usually off (as in i overspent and also overestimated how much money i was going to make), but it’s usually not &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; bad, ha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-2-plan-for-the-next-year&quot;&gt;part 2: plan for the next year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reconfigure-calendar&quot;&gt;1. reconfigure calendar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;based on my values and time review, i reconfigure my weekly calendar flow. i’m pretty neurotic about this and i certainly don’t think everyone could or shuld be likethis, but it’s what work for me&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[insert screenshot]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i think this year i might also throw in a monthly calendar flow… i’m feeling bold, lol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;update-budget&quot;&gt;2. update budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;make adjustments based on future job prospects, things i want to do, amount i want/need to travel, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;archive--organize-all-my-files&quot;&gt;3. archive &amp;amp; organize all my files&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;clean up, clean up, everybody everywhere&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;launch-projects&quot;&gt;4. launch projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;over the course of the year, i’ve gathered a list of ideas for things i want to do next year. this year, i’m going to start out day 3 of my retreat by putting in a bunch of initial energy to get some of those projects off the ground. i imagine it’ll look mostly like start-up infrastructure, but i’m excited to see what comes of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and that’s all folks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* sometimes i think this is a pretty selfish thing to do. but i’ve realized two things over time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;part of my theory of change is that systemic change begins at the smallest scale possible. often that is at the internal level of a single individual.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;as i’ve watched and learned about the failures of different movements, the well-being of the movement seems to correlate strongly with the well-being of the leader(s). imo social structures are fractcals of the people at their core. so getting right with yourself only helps your work. when you have a good system for yourself, every tiny little decision has ripple effects in the work around you.  conversely, not being right internally makes it real easy to have the work around you not be right.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;writing data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;mbtablestyle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;writing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;47:42&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;spell-check, link-finding, &amp;amp; formatting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5:52&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">a few people have asked what this is so i figured it was time to write it out. i’ve found that one of the highest values of writing out my thoughts is being able to direct people to them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">on friends and death</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/on-friends-and-death/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="on friends and death" /><published>2016-12-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/on-friends-and-death</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/on-friends-and-death/">&lt;p&gt;while on this death kick, i remembered that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Moral_letters_to_Lucilius/Letter_63&quot;&gt;letter LXIII (63) from seneca, on grief for lost friends&lt;/a&gt;, addressed the topic of friends and grief. it had some pretty great insights as they related to death. i think i’ll just put down each quote and then my little reflection after each one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-the-most-of-friends-while-theyre-still-alive&quot;&gt;making the most of friends while they’re still alive​​&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So, my dear Lucilius, behave in keeping with your usual fair-mindedness and stop misinterpreting the kindness of fortune. She has given as well as taken away. Let us therefore go all out to make the most of friends, since no one can tell how long we shall have the opportunity. Let us just think how often we leave them behind when we are setting out on some long journey or other, or how often we fail to seem them when we are staying in the same area, and we shall realize that we have lost all too much time while they are till alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/145892324822/hugs&quot;&gt;this is the reason i hug people so fiercely&lt;/a&gt;. every time you leave someone, you never know if that’s the last time you’ll see them. we should act like that every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this is also part of the thrust behind my “go big/go deep or go home” mantra. that started with me from my tallahassee christian youth group crew (mostly roshad), but now has taken on this added meaning. since this might be the last time i see you, let’s make the most of the time we have now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;some people might think that would get exhausting. and maybe it does. but in the ten-ish years i’ve been living like that, it has yet to get exhausting to me. if anything, it makes people (myself included) happier to see someone that next time. it makes it feel more like a gift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;finally, this phenomenon of not seeing people while they’re in town and then when they’re gone (whether they move or die) is hilarious to see written about during the time of seneca’s life, 4 B.C. to 65 a.d.* so knowing that it’s been a problem forever, we just need to make active decisions to change it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this is a big part of why i’ve decided to just get very clear (sometimes painfully explicit, even to myself) with who my close friends are. then i set up regular hang out sessions with them so that i don’t fall into this trap. it’s tough, but you really can’t be close with everyone all the time. so it’s better, imo, to just look that in the face and deal with it in a concrete way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;friends-stay-with-you-even-after-death&quot;&gt;friends stay with you even after death&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Let us see to it that recollection of those we have lost becomes a pleasure to us. Nobody really cares to cast his mind back to something which he is never going to think of without pain. Inevitable as it is that the names of persons who were dear to us and are now lost should cause us a gnawing sort of pain when we think of them, that pain is not without a pleasure of its own. As my teacher Attalus used to say, ‘In the pleasure we find in the memory of departed friends there is a resemblance to the way in which certain bitter fruits are agreeable or the very acidity of an exceedingly old wine has its attraction. But after a certain interval all that pained us is obliterated and the enjoyment comes to us unalloyed.’ … Thinking of departed friends is to me something sweet and mellow. For when I had them with me it was with the feeling that I was going to lose them, and now that I have lost them I keep the feeling that I have them with me still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it’s interesting that we do think of death as this irreversible moment that changes things forever. and, to be sure, it definitely does. but sometimes i find myself or hear others discussing death like we’re going to forget. but, like seneca said, my experience has shown that not to be true. people who i’m really close to and are alive have basically the same relationship to me and my thoughts when they’re dead. i’ve only had a few friends die so far, but the ones that i thought about often were that way because our lives were intertwined in such an intense way for so long that many things remind me of them. whether or not they’re alive, those things still remind me of them. similiarly, friends i don’t think about often are that way before or after their death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-can-happen-at-any-time-today--death-doesnt-play-by-seniority&quot;&gt;what can happen at any time today / death doesn’t play by seniority​&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I realize now that my sorrowing in the way I did was mainly due to the fact that I had never considered the possibility of his dying before me. That he was younger than I was, a good deal younger too, was all that ever occurred to me – as if fate paid any regard to seniority! So let us bear it constantly in mind that those we are fond of are just as liable to death as we are ourselves…  Now I bear it in mind not only that all things are liable to death but that that liability is governed by no set rules. Whatever can happen at any time can happen today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i totally fall into this trap all the time. somehow, i expect that people will die in a linear order from oldest to youngest. experience has obviously proven that to be otherwise, but i get it. the general trend is that the older people get, the more likely it is that they will die due to a body that’s unable to bounce back. and yet, people die of the unexpected and uncontrollable all the time. not only that, but it seems like the number of people i know who are getting and dying from cancer at early ages is skyrocketing. maybe i’m wrong, but i can see it happening all around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so this idea that people die off in age order really just isn’t that helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;phew. that took longer and is longer than i expected it would be, but, hey, i’m on vacation. i’ll write as long as i want i guess, heh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*  we, definitely myself included, like to imagine that “things were different back then,” but they just weren’t. the problems we’re dealing with now seem to have been the problems we’ve been dealing with for all of time. they might look different, but it seems increasingly clear that they’re the same problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;writing: 24:23
spell-check, link-finding, &amp;amp; formatting: 23:02&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">while on this death kick, i remembered that letter LXIII (63) from seneca, on grief for lost friends, addressed the topic of friends and grief. it had some pretty great insights as they related to death. i think i’ll just put down each quote and then my little reflection after each one.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">my (first) deathnote</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/my-first-deathnote/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="my (first) deathnote" /><published>2016-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/my-first-deathnote</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/my-first-deathnote/">&lt;p&gt;sidenote: this post and the next one or two i write (i think) are both going to be about death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i’m fairly obsessed with the american anti-obsession with death. the lengths american society goes to to avoid thinking about, dealing with, seeing in real ways, and coping with the fact that we’re all going to die one day are amazing. i think a large portion of the issues american society faces flow from this aversion. i could go on and on about this, but that’s not the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the point today is to start dealing with it myself. and i’ll start with my own death (because i almost always think the place to start in in oneself). i think this may become an annual tradition. who knows. here goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it’s nearing the end of 2016 and i’m thinking about my death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;my first thought: i am resigned to the reality that one way or another, the oppressive systems we live in will probably kill me. if it’s not a bullet or other direct assault from a human it may be the climate and resulting catastrophe or it may be cancer from the toxic environments/lifestyles we’ve created for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so be it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or maybe I’ll die of old age and my body ceasing to function in a way that keeps my soul in it. that’s fine, too. it feels less likely, but hey, nothing’s impossible. and maybe i’ll look back at this when i’m 90 and think “what a ridiculous thing i wrote.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;either way, this note about my death is actually about how i want to live (knowing that i will die):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;i hope that some people i crossed paths with know what it feels like to be loved because of me&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;i hope that people and the world are better because of my life, relationships, and work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;i would love to be a part of ending hunger worldwide&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;i hope to be part of bringing about new ways of living that help people live lives more aligned with their true selves, people arond them, and the planet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if there’s an afterlife, i hope that the things i did while alive land me on the side of it where there’s contentment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;whether i die later today, tomorrow, or in some years, i hope i’m able to genuinely &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/141849731677/timelines-of-change-living-everyday-like-its-the&quot;&gt;live every day like it’s my last and also like i’ll live till i’m old&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ps - also, i didn’t commit suicide. if shit gets crazy, don’t let anyone tell you i killed myself. i will never kill myself. if you hear it on tape, i was tortured. i promise. &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/141082081412/two-defining-factors%5D&quot;&gt;i have already died once&lt;/a&gt; and that experience taught me that life is much too precious to willingly end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stories.californiasunday.com/2015-04-05/death-redesigned&quot;&gt;death, redesigned&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcodesign.com/3044079/asides/ideo-tried-to-redesign-dying-and-instead-ended-up-with-death-yurts&quot;&gt;the backlash to death, redesigned&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/151880430857/america-a-nation-founded-on-genocide-and-trauma&quot;&gt;america: a nation founded on genocide and trauma that is afraid to acknowledge death and grief&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;writing: 18:36
spell-check, link-finding, &amp;amp; formatting: 9:11&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">sidenote: this post and the next one or two i write (i think) are both going to be about death.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">meditation is like muddy water settling</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/meditation-is-like-muddy-water-settling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="meditation is like muddy water settling" /><published>2016-11-01T06:21:28-04:00</published><updated>2016-11-01T06:21:28-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/meditation-is-like-muddy-water-settling</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/meditation-is-like-muddy-water-settling/">&lt;p&gt;another insight that has stuck with me from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onbeing.org/program/mary-karr-astonished-by-the-human-comedy/8972/&quot;&gt;the mary karr episode of on being&lt;/a&gt; is from the following paragraph (so glad the on being podcast episodes have &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onbeing.org/program/mary-karr-astonished-by-the-human-comedy/transcript/8975#main_content&quot;&gt;full transcripts&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;DR. KARR: Yeah. I love that. I mean, I love that thing Thomas Keating says about practicing mindfulness, and that it’s sort of like — there’s a bunch of water that has mud and silt in it, and the longer you practice, the more that just kind of settles to the bottom, and you don’t feel any peace. You might practice for days and weeks, and it’s just cloudy and noisy. And he says what you don’t realize is that healing is happening, that that stuff — by doing that, you are settling it, but you don’t notice it because it hasn’t settled yet. You have to just — how difficult just to keep sitting there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this has been exactly how meditation has benefitted me over the last couple of years. i started trying to meditate daily in jan 2015. i hit 250/365 days that year and, as far as i can remember, i’ve meditated 10+ minutes every day this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;at first, i didn’t really notice anything. it didn’t seem like much was changing about anything i could sense or feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;then, during the summer, i started meditating before i went to work. i noticed a significant difference in my ability to assess situations more thoughtfully. i could just see into a situation with more perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;that fall, when i got a new job, i began to notice that i could notice when i wasn’t focused. i would be focusing on a particular work task and then i would feel myself reaching for something unrelated. like… i could sense my brain wander away from what i was doing. or, to be more explicit, i noticed when thoughts crept in that weren’t related to what i was working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;that proved to be unbelievably valuable because i could then either (a) find a way to deal with the distraction (which often just involved writing it down to do later) or (b) put it aside and refocus. either way, both of those options were better than what i would do previously, which was let the thought actually distract me and then snap out of it (texting, facebook, email, twitter, reading random articles) 30+ minutes later and wonder ‘wtf have i been doing?!?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;these two last things i’ve gained from daily meditation are probably the most impactful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by noticing which thoughts wander into my brain during meditation (i.e. what’s on my mind), i’m able to better parse out what is taking up my mental energy.&lt;/em&gt; that allows me to, outside of meditation, handle those things that would have taken up lots of mental energy over the day. i’m then freer to focus on other things with more calm and clarity. the positive impact of this cannot be understated.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;learning to let my thoughts come and go with the trust that the important things will come back when they need to. sometimes during the day i’ll remember something that seems &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; important but i won’t have time to process it properly. then, i would beat myself up and try &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; hard to think of the thing i had forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;it turns out, as i’ve meditated more and more, i’ve noticed that my brain is actually quite adept at not letting me forget &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; important things. the really important things always come back up (often during meditation, but not always). i’m able to process the thought then if i missed it the first time. and if a thought doesn’t come back up, it honestly probably wasn’t that important. now, i know that’s a very common trope that’s often seen as trite, but i’ve really begun to trust it lately and it’s brought a lot more ease to my thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so yea. it really feels like the process of muddy water settling. you don’t necessarily notice it day-to-day, but over time, the ability to see through the increasingly clear water provides huge benefits. you just have to let it settle enough to get there.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">another insight that has stuck with me from the mary karr episode of on being is from the following paragraph (so glad the on being podcast episodes have full transcripts):</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the diversity/bandwidth tradeoff</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-diversity-bandwidth-tradeoff/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the diversity/bandwidth tradeoff" /><published>2016-10-31T06:11:28-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-31T06:11:28-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-diversity-bandwidth-tradeoff</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-diversity-bandwidth-tradeoff/">&lt;p&gt;in the paragraph &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/152509089972/the-four-characteristics-of-the-best-teams&quot;&gt;immediately preceding the one i wrote about yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, the authors describe something called the diversity/bandwidth tradeoff:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“As we expand the diversity of social connections we have, the bandwidth we can commit to each of those connections becomes more limited, and the information that comes from them gets weaker and narrower. And that in turns makes weak ties suitable for certain kinds of work and strong ties suitable for others.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i think about this &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; time. the two most common contexts for me are productivity and social connections, but it comes up in other places, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;on the productivity front, it shows up as needing to make tough choices about priorities (the last part of the quote above about weak ties vs strong ties isn’t really relevant for the productivity front, but it is for the social). it means recognizing that you can’t do everything. and you can really only do a few things at the same time if you want to do any of them well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;on one hand, that reality has to do with amassing resources. building knowledge (and sometimes a network, too) relevant to what it is you’re trying to do requires focus. whether its raising a family or becoming an opera star, the more you can focus, the faster and more deeply you’ll learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;on the other hand, it has to do with creativity. in order to be creative, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ceros.com/blog/the-art-and-science-of-generating-great-ideas/&quot;&gt;our brains actually need to have some open space (as simon martin mentions over on the ceros blog in his recent post on the art and science of generating great ideas)&lt;/a&gt;. when focusing on too many different things, your brain doesn’t have space to make connections because it’s too busy trying to hold information. and as david allen, one of my productivity gurus says, “the brain is a great place for having ideas, not holding them.” you can’t generate new ideas in your lanes of focus if your brain is too busy holding ones you’ve already had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the diversity/bandwidth tradeoff shows up in a parallel way socially to the productivity breakdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;for example, when i was in grad school, &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/145062715257/on-saying-no&quot;&gt;i really tried to do everything&lt;/a&gt;. this resulted in me running myself ragged. &lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/150726651967/turns-out-you-cant-be-good-friends-with-everyone&quot;&gt;what i’ve been learning this year&lt;/a&gt; is that it’s super important (and very counter-cultural) to have a clearly delineated group of close friends and focus on those friendships intensely. yes, this means that being close to everyone is not possible, but it allows three things. (1) it allows us to build the type of deep friendship that we all crave (the “i would drop whatever i’m doing if you needed me” type of friendship). (2) it allows spontaneity in those friendships because you aren’t overcommitted. (3) when do you do hangout with someone outside of your inner circle, it means you can show up fully for that person because you’re not exhausted from giving too much to too many different people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;of course, there is always a balance. it’s not good to only be thinking about just one thing or have just one friend. but most people (&lt;a href=&quot;http://lqb2writes.tumblr.com/post/146158937647/why-i-plan-my-schedule-six-weeks-in-advance&quot;&gt;myself included&lt;/a&gt;) try to do way too much and it undermines their success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sidenote: on this friend front, i think there may be a lot more to this that belongs in another post… for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;maybe this theory is why having a small number of close friends and many distant ones is good.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;i wonder if people and communities would be better if we thought strategically about this from an early age? what if we taught our children that their lives would be the most fulfilling if their thought about their friendships like this? what if the design of our physical communities supported and encouraged friendships like this? hm!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><summary type="html">in the paragraph immediately preceding the one i wrote about yesterday, the authors describe something called the diversity/bandwidth tradeoff:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the four characteristics of the best teams</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-four-characteristics-of-the-best-teams/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the four characteristics of the best teams" /><published>2016-10-30T08:58:28-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-30T08:58:28-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-four-characteristics-of-the-best-teams</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-four-characteristics-of-the-best-teams/">&lt;p&gt;this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.resiliencethebook.com&quot;&gt;resilience book&lt;/a&gt; is pretty dope. the chapter that i’m in now is about resilience groups and teams. after lots of different cases and data, they make this claim about teams (page 187):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The most powerful constellation seems to be to have small, diverse teams of strongly tied collaborators, who each have a large and diverse weak-tie network — the best of both worlds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;they break it down in the chapter differently, but here are the parts of that that seem critical to me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;small&quot;&gt;small&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the team needs to be small enough to not have to coordinate too many pieces. in the last few years of my career, i’ve seen this play out as logisitical coordination RE calendars and locations to meet, but it can show up in other ways, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diverse&quot;&gt;diverse&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;actual and cognitive diversity are really important. they give a team the ability to think deep and wide and make breakthroughs in ways that teams that are too similar can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;strongly-tied&quot;&gt;strongly-tied&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the team members need to be strongly tied. this means that, even though they should have different cognitive abilities, they should be similar enough to work well together. there’s nothing worse than having a dysfunctional team. in fact, i often tell my friends that if their relationship with their boss isn’t a good one, the awesomeness of the work their doing isn’t worth staying. it’s a pattern i’ve seen over and over. but i digress…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;with-many-weak-ties&quot;&gt;with many weak-ties&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;each team member should have a large and diverse network (i.e. many weak ties). this allows the core team to have access to knowledge resources without needing to have them all in house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the more i think about it, the more i think these four points are how to make the world a more beautiful, functional place, while also shifting some of the terror that is the large corporation. maybe this thinking could/should play out in how we structure our social lives and physical communities as well.
hm!&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">this resilience book is pretty dope. the chapter that i’m in now is about resilience groups and teams. after lots of different cases and data, they make this claim about teams (page 187):</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">cognitive diversity, actual diversity, and the benefits of both</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cognitive-diversity-and-actual-diversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="cognitive diversity, actual diversity, and the benefits of both" /><published>2016-10-29T07:03:28-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-29T07:03:28-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cognitive-diversity-and-actual-diversity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cognitive-diversity-and-actual-diversity/">&lt;p&gt;pages 204-208 in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.resiliencethebook.com&quot;&gt;resilience&lt;/a&gt; have two really fascinating cases that make two astounding points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cognitive diversity on a team can compensate for and even create better outcomes than intelligence on a team, and 
actual diversity and cognitive diversity together can be mutually reinforcing and beneficial. 
so what does all that mean? i’ll explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cognitive-diversity&quot;&gt;cognitive diversity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;scott page is a professor of complex systems, political science, and economics and the university of michigan. he defines cognitive diversity as such: the distribution of different kinds of thinkers within a group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;kevin dunbar, a psychologist at the university of toronto, studied cognitive diversity and its impacts on team performance. turns out that having a team with a high (but not too high) level of cognitive diversity can create higher levels of performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;dunbar took two scientific research labs and studied them in their actual research environments. team x had a high level of overall intelligence but a relatively narrow range of scientists. team y had a much more diverse set of scientists (i’m not sure how the intelligence level compared). the labs have no connection to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;at one point, teams x and y ran into a similar problem. team y, the cognitively diverse team, solved the problem in two minutes at a single meeting. team x was still struggling with the problem two months later. i can only imagine how much time and progress team x wasted trying to solve a problem that team y solved in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;dunbar’s theory is that having different ways to think about a problem allows more access to alternative thinking about potential solutions. when people in a group think similarly, for example, they tend to use similar and more complex metaphors to describe situations because they have shared understanding of the knowledge required to make sense of them. teams with different thinking and backgrounds tend to use more basic but wide ranging types of metaphors in order to spam knowledge gaps between members. this allows more diverse ways of thinking about the same problem which seems to lead to solution faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;now all of this said, there are certainly tradeoffs to having more diverse teams over similar teams. as with everything, there’s a balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;teams with low cognitive diversity have low startup costs because they share language and knowledge. the means they can probably move faster when things are going well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;teams with high cognitive diversity have high communications cost. they can’t easily explain their thinking to others without shared backgrounds so they spend extra time doing so. however, the benefit that that creates is ability to blast through problems quickly, as opposed to getting bottle-necked by a lack of ability to think outside the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;actual-diversity&quot;&gt;actual diversity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in a similar way, “actual” diversity (gender, class, race, etc.) also has benefits. the example used in the book was about gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;when men find lab surprising lab results, they tend to assume they know why and keep moving forward (in my opinion, this is an effect of socialization, not physiology). either way, this pattern has the effect of sending teams down wrong pathways. incorrect early assumptions lead to wasted time down the road and makes it difficult to backtrack to find mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;women, however, tend to try to stop and explain surprising results by doing more rigorous testing. by looking for ways to recreate the results, they generate more firm data and thus a higher ability to explain results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;now, from the outside, this may look like women are slower or less aggressive researchers. however, in reality, women are just as aggressive about their research; they just go about the work in completely different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;holy shit, that took 30 minutes to write. :O&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">pages 204-208 in resilience have two really fascinating cases that make two astounding points:</summary></entry></feed>
